<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Army anatomized: or, A brief &amp; plain display of the humble, honest and religious actings of the General Sir Tho. Fairfax, and his army of saints, toward the good of the King and Parliament, and the whole kingdom, since the famous victory, at Naseby, June 14. 1645. Occasioned upon the serious consideration of 4 Scripture-properties of every true saint and Christian soldier. 1. Whatsoever ye would that men should do unto you ('tis our Saviors own Golden-Rule) even so do ye unto them. Mat. 7. 12. 2. Not to do any evil (a general Rule, which admits of no exception, either in Kings, or in Commanders) that good may come thereof. Rom. 3.8. 3. To abstain from every appearance of evil; much more from every apparent evil. 2 Thes. 5. 22. 4. Do violence, or wrong, to no man; neither accuse any man falsly. Luke 3.14. Now, how Sir Tho. Fairfax's army of saints and Christian soldiers have performed all these, or any of these, shal be faithfully and plainly declared, in 20. following observations. / By a loyal lover of peace and truth; but a hearty contemner of sedition and schism.</title>
            <author>Loyal lover of peace and truth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92927</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E419_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203539</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863474</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863474</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115676</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92927)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115676)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 66:E419[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Army anatomized: or, A brief &amp; plain display of the humble, honest and religious actings of the General Sir Tho. Fairfax, and his army of saints, toward the good of the King and Parliament, and the whole kingdom, since the famous victory, at Naseby, June 14. 1645. Occasioned upon the serious consideration of 4 Scripture-properties of every true saint and Christian soldier. 1. Whatsoever ye would that men should do unto you ('tis our Saviors own Golden-Rule) even so do ye unto them. Mat. 7. 12. 2. Not to do any evil (a general Rule, which admits of no exception, either in Kings, or in Commanders) that good may come thereof. Rom. 3.8. 3. To abstain from every appearance of evil; much more from every apparent evil. 2 Thes. 5. 22. 4. Do violence, or wrong, to no man; neither accuse any man falsly. Luke 3.14. Now, how Sir Tho. Fairfax's army of saints and Christian soldiers have performed all these, or any of these, shal be faithfully and plainly declared, in 20. following observations. / By a loyal lover of peace and truth; but a hearty contemner of sedition and schism.</title>
                  <author>Loyal lover of peace and truth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 4".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, --  Baron, 1612-1671 --  Military leadership --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115676:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Seria Exercitus Series.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Army Anatomized: OR, A brief &amp; plain <hi>Diſplay</hi> of the humble, honeſt and religious Actings of the General Sir <hi>Tho. Fairfax,</hi> and his Army of Saints, toward the good of the King and Parliament, and the whole Kingdom, ſince the famous Victory, at NASEBY, <hi>June</hi> 14. 1645.</p>
            <p>Occaſioned upon the ſerious Conſideration of 4 SCRIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TURE PROPERTIES of every true <hi>Saint</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>Soldier.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>1.</hi> Whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do unto you (<hi>'tis our Saviors own</hi> Golden-Rule) even ſo do ye unto them. <bibl>
                  <hi>MAT. 7.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>2.</hi> Not to do Any Evil (a general-Rule, <hi>which admits of no</hi> exception, <hi>either in Kings, or in Commanders</hi>) that Good may come thereof. <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 3.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>3.</hi> To abstain from every Appearance of Evil; <hi>much more from</hi> every Apparent Evil. <bibl>
                  <hi>2 THES. 5.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>4.</hi> Do Violence, or Wrong, to no man; neither accuſe Any man falſly. <bibl>
                  <hi>LUKE 3.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Now, how Sir THO. FAIRFAX's Army of Saints and Chriſtian Soldiers have performed All Theſe, or any of Theſe, ſhal be faithfully and plainly declared, in 20. following <hi>Obſervations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a loyal <hi>Lover</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Truth;</hi> But a hearty <hi>Contemner</hi> of <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Schiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JUDE 11.</hi>
               </bibl> Wo unto them, for, they have gone in the way of Kain; and ran gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily after the Error of Balaam, for Reward; and periſhed in the Gain-ſaying of Core.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:115676:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115676:2"/>
            <head>THE ARMY <hi>ANATOMIZED.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the moſt renowned fight &amp; glorious victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which the great Lord of Hoſts and God of Battels gave to our <hi>Army</hi> at <hi>Nafeby</hi> (wherein, although, next under God, we muſt give the Noble <hi>General,</hi> Sir THO. FAIRFAX, the prime part of the honor thereof, both for his magnanimity and prudence therein: Yet next unto him, I dare be bold, moſt juſtly, to give as great a ſhare of the honor of that glorious Victory, to valiant and faithful Colonel <hi>Roſſiter,</hi> a brave <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Commander, in the <hi>Northern</hi> parts of the Kingdom, as <hi>Any</hi> Commander, in the whole <hi>Army</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved: Who, in the very nick of a neceſſitous time of the battel, fell in, with his freſh and valiant Troops of Horſe, upon the Kings forces, and by Gods great mercy, gave an admirable turn to the day, for us. And after the happy recovery of the <hi>Weſt</hi> into the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> hands (wherein, alſo, God honored another moſt renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> Commander, even noble and ever to be honored <hi>Major General</hi> MASSEY, with as full a portion of the honor of that Conqueſt, as any the loudeſt boaſting <hi>Independent</hi> or <hi>Sectary</hi> in the whole <hi>Army</hi> (not one excepted) could juſtly challenge to himſelf, ſo whom, let me here all this one more brave badg of honor (the rather, becauſe he now moſt unhappily lies under a cloud of <hi>Englands</hi> groſs ingratitude to him) which, reverend Mr <hi>Vines,</hi> in his famous and moſt learned Funeral Sermon for the ever to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115676:3"/>Lord Gen. <hi>Eſſex,</hi> p. 33. moſt deſervedly engraved upon him, in theſe words. That, renowned <hi>Governor</hi> of <hi>Glocester,</hi> whom I may (borrowing <hi>Cicero's</hi> word) moſt juſtly cal, under God, <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus Regni Stator,</hi> The <hi>Stator of the Kingdom of England;</hi> Becauſe he took the Enemies horſe by the bridle, in his full carreer, and bravely ſtopt him; and being reſolved to ſell <hi>that City</hi> to them by the candle, he was (by the renowned Lord <hi>General</hi> ESSEX) reſcued before the candle dropt out, and thus preſerved the ſaid City, and the whole Kingdom therewith. And (to proceed now) after the reducing of <hi>Exeter</hi> and <hi>Oxford</hi> to the <hi>Parliaments</hi> power (but upon ſuch terms and conditions, as (had not <hi>Cromwel</hi> too boldly urged) the <hi>Parliament</hi> would never have condeſcended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to or owned) O, had the <hi>Army,</hi> now, ſpontaneouſly tendered themſelves in a Chriſtian manner (as that moſt excellent <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Religious Retreat,</hi> moſt worthily noteth) to lay down their Arms, and be diſpoſed of by the <hi>Parllament,</hi> they had crowned the Goſpel and themſelves with perpetual praiſe and honor. But, the <hi>Army</hi> (being upon thoſe Conqueſts too much idolized, almoſt by every body, in City and Country) began, contrariwiſe (with the ſtrong help of the <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> in the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and by the crafty aſſiſtance of Mimical M. <hi>Hugh Peters</hi> (that blazon-ſac'd and blattering <hi>Hocus Pocus,</hi> or bluſtring <hi>jugler</hi> of the <hi>drmy</hi>) who, together, with his other two Brethren in iniquity, <hi>Dell</hi> and <hi>Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marſh</hi> (a triple knot of <hi>Jeſuitical Incendiaries</hi> and <hi>Firebrands</hi> of Sedition and Rebellion) preaching or rather prattling to the Army, among many other their poyſonous poſitions, <hi>That the Earth is the Saints and the fulneſs thereof;</hi> and that they are (now) <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Maſters</hi> of all; and thus encouraging the <hi>Army</hi> to put forth their horns of pride, oppreſſion, hypocriſie and notorious diſſimulation, for the better acting and conniving of their <hi>great Deſign</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Toleration</hi> of all Opinions, <hi>Parity</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity</hi> of all mens eſtates over the whoſe Kingdom, and <hi>Liberty of Conſcience in all Religions;</hi> notwithſtanding that Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Army</hi> had oftentimes, and eſpecially in one of their late Declarations, promiſed and proteſted that they would not have to do with matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> either concerning <hi>Preſbytery</hi> or <hi>Independency,</hi> but would refer themſelves, therein, to the wiſdom and piety of the <hi>Parliament.</hi> Yet notwithſtanding,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115676:3"/>this <hi>grand Deſign</hi> hath been carryed on with ſo much craft and induſtry, by the <hi>Sectaries</hi> both in the <hi>Army, Parliament, City</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> that it was high time for the honeſt and plain hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Preſbyterian-Party</hi> to look about them (and, O that they had done ſo, indeed, and been as zealous for their God, their Covenant and Country, in time, as they ſhould, and (then) might have been) and that, eſpecially, conſidering that the <hi>Army</hi> of our loyal Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Scotland</hi> was moſt honeſtly and peaceably upon their departure out of the Kingdom, but, this our own <hi>Army</hi> remaining, ſtil, in a ſtrong body among us, although no viſible Enemy appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (ſave only <hi>Chymards</hi> and imaginary Enemies of our own contriving) to oppoſe them. The City of <hi>London,</hi> therefore (that main eye-ſore to all the <hi>Deſigns,</hi> formerly, of <hi>Royal Malignants,</hi> and (now of late) of <hi>Seditious Sectaries</hi>) together with many other Counties of the Kingdom, earneſtly and often petition the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that our <hi>Army</hi> might be disbanded, that <hi>Preſbyterian Church-Government</hi> might be (as the <hi>Parliament</hi> had often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed) eſtabliſhed, and that the heavy taxations of the Kingdom (by reaſon, eſpecially of the <hi>Army,</hi> thus, ſtil embodyed) might be eaſed and ended. But the City of <hi>London,</hi> by reaſon of very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and very ſtrange and unexpected (I am ſure moſt undeſerved) <hi>delays</hi> herein; eſpecially, if we (as juſtly we may) cal to mind the <hi>Parliaments</hi> former promiſes to live and dye with the City of <hi>London;</hi> yet, I ſay the City was at length neceſſitated to exhibite to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> a moſt famons, juſt, deliberate and righteous Remonſtrance of theirs and the Kingdoms many grievances and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable diſguſts, in high meaſure offered unto them by the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent</hi> party in <hi>Parliament,</hi> and elſwhere, and eſpecially for the moſt neceſſary disbanding of the <hi>Army,</hi> and for the ſetling of their <hi>City Militia</hi> in the hands and power of ſuch perſons as they might ſafely conſide in; (many <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>neutrally diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted perſons</hi> having then crept in among them, or at leaſt, diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves, then, to be diſaffected to the <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Government</hi>) the City promiſing and aſſuring their readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and cheerfulneſs to raiſe monies for the payment of the <hi>Armies arrears,</hi> if theſe things might immediately be done for them and the Kingdom. For ſatisfaction to all which the Cities deſires (though by the craft and power of the <hi>Independents</hi> in the <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115676:4"/>that famous <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> and their other moſt excellent, neceſſary and honeſt <hi>Petitions</hi> were moſt ſtrangely diſcountenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and ſeandalized, yea and voted to be ſcandalous papers, yet) many fair promiſes were made unto them, but, ſtil, from time to time, obſtructed and retarded, and nothing to any purpoſe done for them, but the City, yea and the whole Kingdom was moſt groſly baffled and deluded by the <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Independent</hi> party and their <hi>noutrakadherents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we ſee;
<q>
                  <l>When God intends; for Sin, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and to laſh,</l>
                  <l>Mens ſheltring Hopes and Helps turnall to traſh.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But now in the firſt place,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to come to the main matter of this our <hi>Army of Saints</hi> (ſo, moſt falſly, called, by proud <hi>Sectaries</hi> themſelves and their ſeduced Ones) And herein alſo not to rake in the dunghil of its moſt deboyſt deportment (for the generality of them) in moſt places where they are quartered, continually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of, almoſt, by all that ſee and truly know them and have had experience of them; both for their moſt beaſtly drunkenneſs, even to vomiting and death, in their drunken vomits; for their frequent andmoſt fearful curſing and ſwearing by no leſs oaths than dam me, wounds, blood and other Cavalierian oaths; their moſt profane ſporting, playing, and fighting deperately one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, even on our <hi>Faſt-days,</hi> yea and <hi>Lords-days</hi> too; and for their moſt abuſive, inſolent and proud refuſal of the moderate, and wholeſom dyet in poor and mean mens houſes, even beyond their abilities, oftentimes. But, I ſay, to omit all theſe to a fitter oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, hereafter, and to take a brief view of the ſeeming faireſt flowers in this <hi>Armies</hi> garden, even of their moſt ſpeciouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended honeſt <hi>Actings,</hi> all along, of late; And, firſt, I ſay, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that <hi>Cromwel</hi> (that fly <hi>Ringleader</hi> to all the <hi>Armies</hi> diſobedience and rebellion) had ſolemnly proteſted and promiſed, oftentimes, even upon his life and honor, in the face of the whole <hi>Houſe of Commons in Parliament,</hi> that the <hi>Army</hi> ſhould and would disband, and lay down all their arms at the doors of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> whenſoever the <hi>Houſe</hi> pleaſed to command them; yet, afterward, when as, upon the many Petitions of the Kingdom to the <hi>Parliament</hi> to have the <hi>Army</hi> disbanded, <hi>Both Houſes of Lords and Commous</hi> ſent to have them disband, they utterly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115676:4"/>refuſed ſo to do, except they might firſt have their <hi>Arrears</hi> payd, and all their own terms and conditions granted unto them; and amongſt them one Condition moſt deſtructive to the <hi>Parliament, viz.</hi> an Act of Indempuity with the Royal Aſſent. As for that late and too ſtale yea falſe and frivolous plea of the <hi>Armies,</hi> that they ſaw an abſolute neceſſity of their not disbanding; becauſe they had diſcovered a moſt deſperate and dangerous Plot againſt their <hi>Army</hi> (as they termed it) and ſo conſequently againſt the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>Kingdom;</hi> this, I ſay, was moſt falſe, and frivolous, and they might as wel perſwade us there were ſtrong, caſtles built in the ayr againſt them, or any ſuch ſtrange <hi>Chymera's</hi> of <hi>non-Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> or things that never were <hi>in rerum natura.</hi> For, (at this time) there was not any ſuch thing objected to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or then once dream't of, to be the cauſe of their not disbanding, but only their want of <hi>Arrears,</hi> and an <hi>Act of Indempnity,</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; neither, to this day, hath or can, any ſuch Plot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or was once mentioned til they (upon this pretence) contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to accuſe the 11. worthy Parliament Members of a plot, who have (to ſome of their faithful friends) taken it on their Salvation, they never had the leaſt thought of any ſuch plot, and as it may eaſily be aſſerted, had no ground or cauſe to intend ſuch a plot. And hath not <hi>Cromwel</hi> (who is, I ſay, believed to be not only the main <hi>Moderator,</hi> but <hi>Machinator</hi> alſo of this and all other the <hi>Armies</hi> principal tranſactions) hath he not here at the firſt, fairly playd the <hi>Saint,</hi> and performed his promiſe to the <hi>Parliament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, notwithſtanding <hi>Irelands</hi> extream neceſſity,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the <hi>Parliaments,</hi> ſtil, earneſt importunity and the <hi>Armies,</hi> ſtil, pretended proclivity to disband, and to have a part of the <hi>Army</hi> ſpeedily ſent away for poor gaſping <hi>Ireland</hi> relief, yet (as was remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly evident in Collonel <hi>Hammonds</hi> andacious demands, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticling with the <hi>Parliament,</hi> upon moſt arrogant and high terms, ere he would ſtir a foot thither; Together with a moſt Seditious and Trayterous <hi>Petition</hi> (as the <hi>Par liament</hi> it ſelf voted it, which was ſubſcribed by a conſiderable <hi>Party</hi> of the <hi>Army</hi>) for a combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of not disbanding, except they might have their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and conditions, firſt granted and confirmed unto them. Yea, notwithſtanding that the Parliament condeſcended herein alſo to them, as much as poſſibly they could for the preſent, and had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115676:5"/>money to pay them as much of their Arrears as poſſibly they could, and promiſed the publike faith of the Kingdom for the reſt, in due time. And thus again, they utterly refuſed to obey the <hi>Parliament,</hi> herein alſo, and would neither disband, nor go to the help and aſſiſtance of that greatly diſtreſſed and almoſt utterly ruinated Kingdom, for want of our help, whatſoever fair Pretences and Proteſtations they made of <hi>Both.</hi> And was not here, think you, an humble and honeſt demeanour of a <hi>Saint-like Army?</hi> And, had not theſe <hi>Saints</hi> ſtrangely forgotten, here, what they have often heard, and therefore ſhould the better have remembred, that the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> (inſpired by the <hi>holy-Spirit</hi> of God) ſaid moſt truly; 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.23. <hi>To obey is better then Sacrifice, and to hearken, then the fat of Rammes. For rebellion is as the ſin of Witcheraft, and ſtubborneſs is as iniquity and idolatry.</hi> Or, can any wiſe or good man believe, that this was a Right and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious way to credit the Goſpel, to Crown themſelves with the Title of <hi>Saints,</hi> or to purchaſe preſent or future prayſes? I ſurely think not.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Well ſaid King David: Truſt not Princes great,</l>
               <l>Nor Sons of Men, prone to delude and Cheat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> notwithſtanding that the <hi>Parliament</hi> (in deep ſenſe of the abſolute neceſſity of the buſineſs of <hi>Ireland</hi>) had after that, again ſent divers <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> in perſon to the <hi>Army</hi> (both for the disbanding of it, as was ſtill promiſed, and mightily now pretended, and days prefixed for the disbanding of ſuch and ſuch Regiments of the <hi>Army;</hi> and for the (ſeeming) ſerious appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating, and preparing of ſuch and ſuch forces of Horſe and Foot, to be ſpeedily diſpatch't away for <hi>Ireland:</hi> Yea, and money pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, (at leaſt 200000. l. of the City of <hi>London,</hi> who ſtill were ready to help the <hi>Parliament</hi> and Kingdom at a dead lift) and that together with thoſe <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> they had ſent alſo <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor General Skippon,</hi> and <hi>Major General Maſſey,</hi> whom the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> had thereupon ordained Commanders in chief of all the Forces in the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> both Horſe and Foot; and notwithſtanding, that divers Commanders and Souldiers were willing to accept that ſervice, and to go under the Command of thoſe brave <hi>Generals;</hi> yet the prime Commanders and Officers of the <hi>Army,</hi> laid unremoveable blocks and obſtructions, again, in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115676:5"/>the way to hinder this work; and unleſs they might change and chooſe their own <hi>Generals,</hi> Commanders and Officers, themſelves, they would not ſtir (by any means, or fair intreaties) nor did not go to this very day. See here then ſtill, the charity of the <hi>Saints</hi> to their diſtreſſed brethren; and their humble obedience to their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream <hi>Maſters,</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> whom thus contemptuouſly and highly they affront, and what could they do more, then (as that excellent <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Religious R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>treat</hi> ſaith) to contemn God himſelf by ſuch moſt palpable obſtinacy and unparalleld <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the <hi>Army</hi> thus now lying lazily ſtil among us,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> moſt heavily burthenſome to the Kingdom, and not having (as was touch't before) any viſible enemy to encounter with, and thus of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ordered by the <hi>Parliament</hi> to disband, but thus obſtinately, and diſobediently refuſing ſo to do, how could they be otherwiſe looked upon, then (as the foreſaid Author ſaid) as <hi>Challengers</hi> of, or <hi>Champions</hi> againſt the Kingdom: And for no little confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this juſt jelouſy, let us take notice of that moſt notable and remarkable affront, yea, Traiterous attempt of this <hi>Saint-like</hi> and Submiſſive <hi>Army</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> acted at <hi>Holmby</hi> in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thampton Shier</hi> (where the King, then, lay and abode by ſpeciall order of <hi>Parliament</hi>) by one <hi>Joyce,</hi> a beggarly Botcher or <hi>Tayler</hi> by <hi>profeſſion,</hi> and but a Reformade Trooper in the Army, &amp;c. who (by a Commanded Troop of 2 or 300, Hourſe, ſent out by the Agitators, and (as tis believed by <hi>Cromwels</hi> direction too, not known to the <hi>General</hi> till afterwards) moſt deſperately and traiterouſly undertook to come ſuddainly to <hi>Holmby,</hi> and there moſt audaciouſly, aſſaulted and ſet upon the King in his very bed-Chamber, ſcarcely ſuffering his Majeſly to take his reſt that night, and ſo beſetting the Houſe with a ſtrong armed guard of his own, Col. <hi>Graves,</hi> who was placed there by authority of the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of both Kingdoms, being for his own peace and ſafety for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to fly away, his own Souldiers (having been before hand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched by the Agitators) baſely deſerting him) the next mourning betimes he violently forced the King out of his bed, ſeized on his Royal perſon (and all this without, yea, contrary to the power and authority of the <hi>Parliament</hi>) and forcibly carryed him and the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> of both Kingdoms, as priſoners along with him
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115676:6"/>into the <hi>Army;</hi> where moſt Trayterouſly they carryed his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty Captive to and fro with them whereſoever they rambled, juſt almoſt as <hi>Tamberlain</hi> carryed <hi>Amurathes</hi> the great <hi>Turk</hi> up and down in triumph, in an <hi>Iron-Cage.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Thus have we ſeen Peſants in pomp to ride,</l>
               <l>Whiles Princes poorly lackey it by their ſide.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Fiftly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> the <hi>Armies General</hi> himſelf, (though when he heard of this moſt Trayterous prank, thus acted by ſuch an obſcure and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour fellow; he ſeemed utterly to diſclaim the knowledg of it, aſſent unto it, or aſsiſtance in it, yet) although, as <hi>General,</hi> he might or ſhould have executed <hi>Martial-Law</hi> upon that Traytor <hi>Joyce,</hi> and ſome of his chief accomplices, and inſtantly to have hang'd them up (the beſt way to have clear'd his integrity there in) for ſo Traiterous a fact, and unſufferable an affront againſt the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> and for ſo audatious an attempt and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the <hi>Army,</hi> without his <hi>Generals</hi> order or allowance: yet was ſo far from it, as that inſteed of being preſently hanged (as he moſt juſtly deſerved) he hath bin advanced (as is generally reported and affirmed) to a <hi>Captains place</hi> at leaſt, and is made one of the <hi>Agitators</hi> of the <hi>Army.</hi> At this time alſo, <hi>Cromwel</hi> had got the <hi>Parliament</hi> (though with much a do upon his engagement for the <hi>Armys</hi> obedience) to vote that no forces ſhould be raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Army,</hi> nor any thing done to diſtate them, juſt when the King was (thus) ceaſed on, and ſtolen away without leave. And he and <hi>Peters</hi> being come to the <hi>Army,</hi> at their <hi>Randez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouze</hi> neer <hi>Newmarket,</hi> told his Regiment and others of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> that this was the beſt days work that ever <hi>England</hi> ſaw, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thus, the Kings being thus got into their hands. And yet for all this, the <hi>General</hi> (in a Declaration publiſh't under his own hand in print) excuſed the whole <hi>Army</hi> from the knowledg of theſe things, although it was credibly aſſured by ſome of his own Regiment, that the party of Horſe, aforeſaid, that took the King, was of 8, out of every Troop in the <hi>Army.</hi> Only thus much, I muſt ingenuouſly acknowledg of the <hi>Generals</hi> ingenuity, that he was willing to diſpoſe of the King back again, as the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould order it, till <hi>Cromwel</hi> (as tis generally reported) alter'd it otherwiſe. And were not here now to moſt <hi>Sanctimonious Acts</hi> of humility and juſtice in this <hi>Army</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> ſo arrogantly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115676:6"/>and audaciouſly in a moſt high meaſure to affront the <hi>Parliament</hi> in thus, not only wreſting the King moſt violently out of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments</hi> power and cuſtody; but ſo highly encouraging the fact, as to manifeſt to the whole world that high treaſon and boldeſt rebellion, are no criminal offences but famous Virtues in this Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his <hi>Army</hi> of <hi>Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, after all this, the noble Lord <hi>Damforlin,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> one of the <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Commiſſioners,</hi> appointed by both <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> to be one of the <hi>Attendants,</hi> on the King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perſon, as a <hi>Commiſſioner,</hi> was moſt highly affronted, and much abuſed by a party of the <hi>Saints</hi> of this <hi>Army,</hi> who now under <hi>Whalty,</hi> boldly guarded the King, and would not ſuffer him to ſpeak with his <hi>Majeſty</hi> (as was fit he ſhould) but when they pleaſed, and as they pleaſed, and they muſt hear whatſoever he had to ſay to the King, touching any private buſineſſes, and thus at laſt drove him away from his attendance. Yea, and the <hi>Lord Louderdail</hi> alſo, coming as a ſpecial <hi>Meſſenger</hi> or <hi>Embaſſador</hi> to the King from the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> was moſt inſolently abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, by this guard of the <hi>Army</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> about the King: and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in his bed-chamber, where he lay to take his reſt after his journey to the King, and neither ſuffered to ſtay there, nor once to ſpeak with the King to deliver his meſſage, and deſpatch his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs with the King, but was forced immediatly to depart away, without ſo much as, once ſeeing the King. And was not here, then, think you ſtil, a very humble and honeſt <hi>Saint-like Army,</hi> thus to dare to affront all Civil and Moral Conſtitutions of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Kingdoms, for juſt Political purpoſes and cauſes allowed by all Laws of <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Nations?</hi> and only thus boldly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by this holy humble <hi>Independent Army</hi> of <hi>Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Men prone to Pride, Errors and Hereſy,</l>
               <l>Reject all Justice, yea Civility.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Seventhly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Notwithſtanding that the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> both in City and Country had, formerly (but moſt falſly) ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently taxed and reviled the <hi>Preſbyterian Partie,</hi> from time to time (&amp; that but only upon meer ſuppoſitions &amp; ungrounded jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, for too much complying with the <hi>Royaliſts</hi> &amp; <hi>Malignant party,</hi> both in ſubſcriptions of Petitions, and other ſuch like Combinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as things not to be admitted in point of Conſcience, nor to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115676:7"/>be endured by them. Yet, now that they have gotten the King into their power and poſſeſſion, they themſelves, not only moſt notoriouſly complywith and give ſtrange allowance to <hi>Royaliſts</hi> and <hi>Malignants</hi> of all ſorts and degrees to come to the King, and to have ordinary and familiar recourſe unto him (which, as you heard before, they utterly denyed to the whole <hi>Preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian State</hi> and Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in their <hi>ſpecial Meſſenger,</hi> or <hi>Embaſſador</hi>) but, which is far more tranſcendently notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in this <hi>Army</hi> of precious and reforming <hi>Saints,</hi> they alſo permit moſt deſperately <hi>Malignant Prelatical Doctors of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity,</hi> the Kings former <hi>Chaplains</hi> to preach before him (which they judg, they ſay, moſt juſt and reaſonable for the Kings out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and inward contentment, though againſt particular or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to the contrary) and to wait upon him; yea, and which is yet more notorious and remarkably audacious in them (it being moſt directly againſt the <hi>Ordinances,</hi> power and authority of the <hi>Parliament</hi>) they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ow unto the King, the <hi>Common-Prayer Book,</hi> in moſt full and ample uſe of it, with all <hi>Prelatical Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remenies</hi> in and about it, and the like alſo is allowed by this <hi>Army of Saints,</hi> and <hi>Godly party,</hi> both at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and divers other places, where the <hi>Army</hi> quarters; Abſolutely contrary, I ſay, to our ſolemn and ſacred <hi>Covenant</hi> and to the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of <hi>Parliament;</hi> and, that which, I am ſure, the <hi>Preſbyterian party</hi> neither did, nor in conſcience durſt allow unto the King when he was in their guard and cuſtody. And is not this (as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Auther</hi> of the <hi>Religious Retreat</hi> truly ſayes) to build with one hand and to pluck down with another, to ſeem at leſt, to ſet up again, what God and the State (with much pains and many prayers) would have utterly raced and ruinated from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us; Surely (as he goes on) when God gives the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to his <hi>Saints,</hi> he wil not ſuffer them to give ſuch large <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerations</hi> to ſinful humane <hi>inventions</hi> in his pure and holy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, nor, like <hi>dogs to return to their old vomit.</hi> This undoubtedly muſt needs blaſt the too high eſteem of your <hi>Army</hi> in the hearts of good men, who verily beleeve theſe things cannot be of God. And this makes all moſt juſtly to cry aloud to our hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Parliament,</hi> in theſe words, (which that reverend and religions <hi>Author</hi> gave his Reader in Latin but I have Engliſhed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115676:7"/>thus) <hi>Take heed, O take heed, moſt noble Senators, and Fathers of your Country, as ye tender the high honor of our eternal God, leaſt whiles ye ſeem to ſettle a preſent Peace, yea utterly loſe an everlaſting Peace.</hi> And ſo ſay I;
<q>
                  <l>Take heed, all ye that deal with Schiſmaticks:</l>
                  <l>Troy found, in Grecian Guifts, deſtructive tricks.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Eighthly, This <hi>Army of Saints,</hi> thus domineering,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> and doing what they pleaſe, the <hi>General,</hi> with his <hi>Councel of War,</hi> and brave (or rather beggarly) <hi>Agitators,</hi> which, now, make up a <hi>pretty Picture</hi> and repreſentation of the three Eſtates of a <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial petty Parliament</hi> (whereby, we are now in great fear to be mainly governed, if not timely prevented) begin to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe <hi>Rules</hi> (I had almoſt ſaid, to make <hi>Laws</hi>) to the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and they muſt, now, be preſently voted and avouched to be the <hi>Parliaments Army</hi> and it <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> ſole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander and Diſpoſer of all the Forts, Cinqueports and ſtrong holds of the Kingdom, and a ſubſtantial courſe taken to pay them their Arrears with certainty and conſtancy, from time to time; But yet, this is not enough (conſidering all the diſtoyal ſervice, thus, already done to and for the <hi>Parliament</hi>) to make the <hi>General,</hi> as it were, the <hi>Vice-Roy,</hi> or Soveraign and ſole Commander of the whole Kingdom, and to make or repute the <hi>Army,</hi> the principal <hi>Propugnators</hi> and <hi>Defenders</hi> of the whole Realms ſafety and felicity; But Petitions muſt alſo be preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and reported to be exhibited to the <hi>General,</hi> and his humble <hi>Sainted Army,</hi> from all Counties and Quarters (whereas, in very deed, as tis wel known, it was but at moſt, a <hi>Sectarian</hi> bluſtring plot of ſome few inponſiderable <hi>Anabaptists, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents</hi> and ſuch like Jugling <hi>chiſmaticks</hi> in ſome few Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties the fixſt of thoſe Petitions to the Army was ſet on foot at <hi>Bechyn</hi> in <hi>Eſſex</hi> by ſeditious Mr <hi>Salt marſh</hi>) thus to make a huge noiſe to blinde the eyes and daunt the heart, if it might be, of too credulous people) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> protection and preſervation of their pretended Peace and Liberties or rather moſt licienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Libertiniſm,</hi> in their ſaid Petitions, proſſering and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing to the <hi>General</hi> All their homage and honor, as to their <hi>ſole Salvator,</hi> in way of bounden gratitude? Yea, and now the <hi>General</hi> himſelf, in his own name (only with the teſtimony
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115676:8"/>or ſubſcription of his principal <hi>Secretary, Worth-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-ruſh</hi>) ſending forth his <hi>Deelartaions</hi> (alias, <hi>Proclamations,</hi> like a <hi>King,</hi> indeed) both to the Parliament and People, to ſhew his powerful <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,</hi> or rather, <hi>Commands;</hi> to all form and degrees of men, whomſoever, as he ſent a very plain and peremptory Summons to the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> that they ſhould give way to or comply with his <hi>Armies</hi> Proceedings, or elſe the blood and miſery, that would befal the City, muſt be upon their own heads, not upon the <hi>Armies.</hi> And as they did, eſpecially in <hi>August</hi> laſt, 1647, in a moſt emment and tranſcendent manner of boldneſs, even to the <hi>Parliament it Self,</hi> in a book, intituled, A <hi>Declaration</hi> from Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and <hi>Propoſals</hi> agreed on by the <hi>Councel</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> to be preſented to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as the <hi>Armies deſires</hi> (or, I ſay; <hi>Commands</hi>) to the <hi>Parliament</hi> for the ſetling of a juſt and laſting Peace; ſay they, but, ſo ſays not God, <hi>Eſay</hi> 57.21. For, among many moſt unſufferable and inſolent <hi>Propoſals</hi> of turning the <hi>Triennial Parliament,</hi> ſetled by an act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> into a <hi>Biennial,</hi> and that, with ſuch bold and licentious <hi>limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> as they themſelves pleaſe to preſcribe; regulating our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Laws,</hi> and <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Justice;</hi> the <hi>Militia</hi> of the <hi>whole Kingdom;</hi> and generally all matters of higheſt concernment both by Land and Sea, in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> yea, I ſay, theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering <hi>Keiſars</hi> take upon them, as it were, to make and manage all Laws almoſt, and to regulate us all, according to their humor and pleaſure. But, among all the reſt, I cannot (nay, who can chooſe) but take ſpecial notice of their horrible and helliſh impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt God and true <hi>Religion, Propoſal</hi> 12. pag. 9. (And ſo, alſo, in their laſt ſort of <hi>Propoſals,</hi> Propoſ. 9. pag. 13. againſt <hi>Conformity in Rellgion</hi>) Where they moſt wickedly deſire a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal of all Acts of <hi>Parliament,</hi> or <hi>Clauſes</hi> of <hi>any Acts,</hi> impoſing any penalties upon men or women for not coming to Church; or for meetings, elſwhere (that is, in private Comers, Houſes Shops, Cellars or Barns) for prayer, or other religious duties, exerciſes, or ordinances (that is) of any kind whatſoever; whether, <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral, Seditious, Idolatrosu, Plasphemous, yea or Trayterous too,</hi> if upon pretence of <hi>Religion</hi> (for, there's no <hi>exception</hi> of any one of theſe, in that or any other the <hi>Propoſals</hi>) whereby, men may (thus) run head long to hel, by authority, and no man dare to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115676:8"/>moleſt, or ſtay them. O moſt abominable and deſperately accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Propoſal,</hi> hateful to God and men! I have read of <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> King of <hi>Aragon,</hi> a famous <hi>Prince,</hi> who hearing a Gentleman; in his Court, pleading againſt <hi>Learning,</hi> and eſpecially that it was unfit for Courtly Lords and Gentlemen to be trained up in <hi>litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or to be <hi>learned Schollars;</hi> he, in high indignation thereat, cryed out, preſently, <hi>That it was the Voyce of an Ox, not of a man.</hi> And, certainly, whoſoever (that has the leaſt <hi>ſpark</hi> of <hi>piety</hi> or <hi>grace,</hi> and) reads or hears of this moſt helliſh <hi>Propoſal,</hi> muſt needs moſt pathetically cry out, in extream abhorrency thereof; <hi>O the voyce of ſome accurſed Turk or apostate Julian, not of a Saint or profeſſed Christian!</hi> Yet, thus, you ſee how like moſt inſolent and arrogant <hi>Rebels</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and all <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> to <hi>Religion</hi> and the whole <hi>Realm,</hi> this <hi>Army</hi> of Saints dares do or deſire any thing to be done, be it ever ſo deſtructive to Chriſtanity or Civil Policy, their deſires they muſt have granted, <hi>per fas aut nofas,</hi> what care they, being <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Conquerors of All.</hi> Hence, then I conceive, any man may clearly conclude; that,
<q>
                  <l>If monſtrous Pride and groſs Impiety</l>
                  <l>Be ſigns of Saints, Theſe (then) are Saints moſt high.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Ninthly, But, for the yet more ſubtile corroboration and ſtrengthning of their wicked deſign of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Toleration;</hi> the <hi>General,</hi> the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> and <hi>Agitators</hi> (having, thus, as is aforeſaid, <hi>felt the pulſes of the people,</hi> in many places, as they rambled up and down, to be all for <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Freedom from Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations,</hi> and that, almoſt, upon any conditions) they do firſt, moſt illegally accuſe 11. of the moſt loyal, active and faithful <hi>Preſbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Members</hi> of the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> (and nothing wil pleaſe them, but a preſent expulſion of them out of the Parliament, though the <hi>Parliament</hi> Voted they could not, either in Law or Conſcience do it) as <hi>Complotters</hi> or <hi>Contrivers</hi> of a <hi>Second</hi> or <hi>New War</hi> (the grand <hi>Anvil</hi> whereon, now, they muſt hammer and hatch all their ſubſequent miſchievous plots) thus, by the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry name of a <hi>Second War</hi> (ſo oppoſite and odious to <hi>deſired peace</hi>) to render thoſe worthy Gentlemen, and all that in this ſort, they muſt, now, hereafter have to do with all, the more odious and contemptible to all people both in City and Country: Whereas, 'tis moſt apparent to God and the rightly intelligent whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115676:9"/>that the <hi>Army it ſelf</hi> was the only riſe and <hi>original cauſe</hi> of all our fears and jealouſies of a <hi>Second War,</hi> by their ſo bold and rebellious refuſal to disband, at the <hi>Parliaments</hi> juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand thereof, as alſo upon their moſt notorious denial to be leſſened in their numbers, yea though it were for the moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitous helping of the poor gaſping and dying Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> then, in moſt ſad diſtreſſes, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Thus, Pride, and Malice, and Impiety,</l>
               <l>Are ne'er without deep ſtrains of Policy.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> therefore, in the tenth, and next place, They began to quarrel with the City of <hi>London,</hi> alſo, which had been (O im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious ingratitude) even their principal <hi>Foster-Fathers,</hi> as I may wel ſay, both, in making them an <hi>Army,</hi> at the firſt, and alſo in maintaining them, in no ſmal meaſure, all along, ever ſince they were firſt <hi>New medelld</hi> to this very day; And the ground of this their quarrel muſt be, their ſecret complotting alſo with thoſe 11. worthy Members of <hi>Parliament,</hi> for the advancing and ſetting forward of the foreſaid <hi>Second War,</hi> and, to this end, their procuring of an unjuſt power (ſays the <hi>Army</hi>) from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> for the alteration and managing of their own <hi>City Militia,</hi> thereby to place and diſplace, to put in or put out whom they pleaſed; and that thereupon they had thruſt out of their <hi>Militia,</hi> divers precious deſerving men (ſays the <hi>Army</hi>) men without all exception, and moſt worthy to be confided in (whereas, indeed, they were known <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> ſome of them preachers, yea ſome of them countenancing <hi>Paul Beſts</hi> abominable blaſphemies, moſt of them, deſperate Enemies to our <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>Reformation</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> as to the point of the power of godlineſs, and of <hi>Presbyterian Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>) and theſe men (ſay they) were thus put out, the better to carry on the <hi>wicked Deſign,</hi> (for ſo they now termed it) <hi>of a Second War,</hi> in the City againſt the <hi>Army,</hi> and ſo conſequently againſt the <hi>whole Kingdom,</hi> and that the City alſo ſecretly liſted Soldiers and conſpired with the 11. accuſed Members and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to occaſion <hi>a freſh effuſion</hi> of blood in the Kingdom: And, thus, by this abominable lying Engine, I ſay, of a <hi>Second War,</hi> which now they cry out of, in all their Letters, Declarations and Remonſtrances to the <hi>Parliament</hi> and people, hereby (as I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115676:9"/>ſaid before) to cry down all juſt defence againſt the <hi>Armies</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>All-overtopping-power,</hi> and thus to cry up more and more their own moſt crafty deſign of <hi>over-mastering all others</hi> that durſt indevor to oppoſe or reſiſt them, with their ſtil continued and ſtrongly embodied <hi>Army;</hi> and yet (which, me thinks, is a moſt ſtrange madneſs in men to beleeve) in all this they muſt be accounted the <hi>only men of peace</hi> in the Kingdom, and the chief protectors of a <hi>Free Parliament,</hi> in its power and priviledges, and of the peoples <hi>Hereditary Liberties:</hi> Whereas, indeed, the clean contrary is moſt evidently true in them, they themſelves mainly and only intending nothing leſs than a <hi>Second or New War,</hi> in caſe they may not have their will of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> in all their Demands, eſpecially in the point of <hi>a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Toleration and Liberty of Conſcience for al men; in all religions,</hi> they being thus (I ſay) in a ſtrong ready body of an <hi>Army;</hi> And having alſo (for a moſt ſtrong confirmation of the truth of all theſe premiſes) brought all their Artillery from <hi>Oxford,</hi> dayly liſting Soldiers of all ſorts, <hi>Cavaliers</hi> and others, poſſeſſing themſelves moſt ſtrongly of all our moſt conſiderable Holds, Forts and Caſtles; And thus, I ſay, moſt evidently reſolving to fight with all that oppoſe them, and to get into their power, by <hi>force,</hi> what they cannot by <hi>fraud</hi> and <hi>hypocriſie.</hi> And thus the poor City of <hi>London</hi> hath <hi>hatcht up a bird to pick out her eyes;</hi> or like the Country-man in the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, <hi>reviv'd a Snake to infest and infect his whole Houſe;</hi> as afterward we ſhal yet more apparently perceive, and ſhew you, in a yet more fit place.</p>
            <q>
               <l>If (ever) Any; Schiſmaticks (indeed)</l>
               <l>In black Ingratitude, do All exceed.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Eleventhly, For the more exquiſitely ripening of their deſign,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> they now moſt craftily began to think how they might get <hi>London</hi> into their clutches, which done, they (and that moſt wiſely) made account all was theirs. Now, this deſign was carryed on with as much egregious craft and <hi>Ieſuitical</hi> ſubtilty, as poſſibly could be. For, firſt, the pretence muſt be, that thoſe 11. <hi>Members of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> accuſed by them, muſt be ſpeedily ſuſpended the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> and not ſuffered to ſit there til they had cleared themſelves of the accuſations, commenced againſt them: But, the <hi>Parliament,</hi> voting the contrary, it preſently threatned by this
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115676:10"/>their <hi>obedient Army of Saints,</hi> that if it were not done (and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently too) as they demanded, they ſhould be forced to exerciſe and make uſe of that power which was in their hands, and in <hi>plain Engliſh,</hi> to compel the <hi>Parliament</hi> to it, whether they would or not; and for that purpoſe, to bring their whole <hi>Army,</hi> toward the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Parliament;</hi> which, how boldly they brought to paſs, and brought their <hi>ſtools with them to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unwillingly welcome</hi> to the City, you ſhal hear and ſee anon in its due place.</p>
            <p>Then,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> in the twelfth place, for the more colourable carrying on of the yet unſeen depth of their deſign, <hi>viz.</hi> the forementioned, quarrel begun againſt the City of <hi>London,</hi> touching their <hi>Militia;</hi> This alſo muſt again be moſt ſtiffly inſiſted on and revived, and thoſe precious men (as the <hi>Army</hi> called them) ſo truſtily to be conſided in, who had been put forth, as aforeſaid, muſt, by all means, be again reſtored to their power and places in the <hi>City-Militia;</hi> or elſe the <hi>Army</hi> (of <hi>modeſt</hi> and <hi>patient, Saints,</hi> who loved not to medle with other mens matters) ſhould be compelled by their power to force and conſtrain the City alſo thereunto. But, withal (good Readers) this muſt be conſidered, by the way; That all the <hi>Armies</hi> warlike preparations to come, now, to the City, their moſt buſie liſting of Soldiers from all parts, to make their <hi>Army</hi> the more numerous and form lable, their ſecuring of <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor</hi> Gaſtle, ſeizing upon and ſecuring the Blook houſes at <hi>Graveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end,</hi> their ſummoning of the Trained Bands of <hi>Eſſen</hi> and <hi>Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>-ſhire to riſe with them; their bringing on of all their Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, and all other war-like proviſions and preparations to beſiege, aſſault and ſtorm the City (if they oppoſed the <hi>Army;</hi> and every preparation for ſelf-defence, which, God and nature afford to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very creature againſt wrong and injury offred or intended to them) all thoſe preparations, I ſay, muſt be beleeved not to be for any hurt to the City, or plunder, or ſpoil thereof. Provided, ſtil, that the City ſtirred not to make any defenſive preparations againſt them, for that muſt be clearly, judged by the <hi>Army</hi> to be the only cauſe of a <hi>Second War,</hi> intended by the City, either in liſting Soldiers, Horſe or Foot, eſpecially not to medle with or entertain into their pay or ſervice, any <hi>Reformadoes</hi> (which the Army it ſelf did and dayly do) whom, the <hi>Army of Saints</hi> and Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115676:10"/>in the City had moſt vilely abriſed, and who therefore were the more likely to do the City the better and more faithful ſervice againſt the <hi>Army;</hi> but, if the City did any of theſe things, this, on the Cities part would, I ſay, be the only means to make a <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond War,</hi> and to occaſion the inevitable eſſuſion of blood, which the <hi>Saint-like Army,</hi> notwithſtanding their mighty preparations for War (on the one ſide) moſt earneſtly and piouſly, like <hi>pune Saints,</hi> indeed, proteſted againſt.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Thus, ſtil, theſe Saints by ſly pretences fair,</l>
               <l>Both Parliament and City do inſnare.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Again, in the thirteenth place,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> that this ſubtile <hi>Army of Saints</hi> may be yet more generally and authoritatively called [over the whole Kingdom] and accounted the only <hi>Peace-makers,</hi> and <hi>Conſervators</hi> of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> riviledges, and <hi>Commons Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties</hi> [as was toucht before in the 8. Obſervation] and ſo griſp the whole power of the Kingdom into their fiſts, and that, both by <hi>Sea</hi> and by <hi>Land,</hi> if poſſibly it might be; the <hi>Army,</hi> moſt audaciouſly, ſends to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and moſt craftily deſire [or rather command] that a <hi>Vote,</hi> and thereupon, an <hi>Ordinance of Parl.</hi> might be paſt that they may be intituled, and acknowledged the <hi>Parliaments Army,</hi> and ſo the Parliament to ſee that they may be payd, from time to time, all their paſt, preſent, and ſuture Arrears, notwithſtanding their <hi>Free-quarter</hi> [which muſt be reckoned for in due time, even <hi>ad Graecas Galendas</hi>] whereſoever they lay, and the body of their <hi>Army</hi> hereupon removed; which was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, and immediately <hi>voted</hi> in <hi>Parliament.</hi> And now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> was made <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> of all the <hi>Forces, Forts, Castles, Cinque-ports,</hi> and <hi>total ſtrength</hi> of all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and under him, his <hi>Councel of War,</hi> and brave <hi>Statesmen</hi> of the Kingdom, the <hi>Mechanick Agitators of the Army,</hi> are thus become <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> over all. And, hereupon, in requital of theſe favors and kindneſſes of the <hi>Parliament</hi> to the <hi>Army,</hi> which hath made them the <hi>Army of the Parliament,</hi> they turn'd it quite the clean contrary way, and made our <hi>Parliament</hi> the <hi>Parliament of the Army;</hi> That is, in plain Engliſh, The <hi>Maſter</hi> is become his <hi>Servants Servant.</hi> And thus now, that no leſs old than true Adagy is here in this our <hi>precious Army</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> moſt exquiſite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fulfilled; <hi>Asperins humili nihil eſt cum ſurgat in altum.</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115676:11"/>Which may be thus Engliſht.</p>
            <q>
               <l>If, once, you ſet a Beggar on horſe-back,</l>
               <l>He'l ride to th' Devil, or his neck ſhal crack.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In ſum,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> in the fourteenth place, obſerve with me, that now, much about this time, or not long after, the grand force to <hi>Both Houſes</hi> (in grateful requital for this the <hi>Parliaments</hi> favor to this <hi>Army of Saints</hi>) was made upon them, by a bold Declaration ſent by the <hi>Army</hi> unto them, in theſe words, or to this effect: <hi>That if they might not have the things they deſired, granted unto them, by ſuch a day, they muſt and would accompliſh them, by ſuch extraordinary ways as God and preſent providence ſhould put them upon.</hi> Only here was all the difference twixt this grand force and the other of the Apprentices, that, the armies was at a diſtance, by a great Army with guns, pikes and ſwords, the other, by a company of young men, at the Parliament doors, but all naked and unarmed, only crying out with their tongues and intreaties not to be accounted traitors for defending themſelves againſt a threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Army. And about this time the <hi>Army</hi> was at <hi>Watford,</hi> with their great guns and formidable artillery, and many of them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 10. miles of <hi>London</hi> which did not a little affright many of the Members away ſhortly after, and ſo by theſe means and ſubtile devices, the <hi>Houſes of Parliament</hi> became their own, and they craftily handled them even as they liſted, almoſt in every thing they pleaſed. For, notwithſtanding the <hi>Parliaments</hi> commands (now, their only <hi>titular or nominal Lords and Maſters</hi>) ſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Army of Saints</hi> (their <hi>ſuppoſed Servants</hi>) more than once or twice, to keep off from quartering neer the City of <hi>London,</hi> by at leaſt 30 or 40 miles diſtance, which, for a little ſeaſon they had done; And notwithſtanding the City of <hi>Londons,</hi> now, chooſing out and ſending <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> to treat with the <hi>Army</hi> (for, to ſuch a height it was now grown, as if the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> had been two diſtinct <hi>advers Parties</hi>) to keep a ſuppoſed and pretended fair correſpondency between them, for peaceable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions; yet, the <hi>Army</hi> (grown, now to a high pitch of power, and now) therefore more apt, eſpecially by their <hi>active Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> to pick quarrels, both with the <hi>Parliament,</hi> their <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Masters,</hi> and with the <hi>City,</hi> their <hi>Foſter-Fathers,</hi> if their <hi>licentious humors</hi> of <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Schiſm,</hi> were croſt ever ſo little)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115676:11"/>holding themſelves much affronted and ſtil much diſcontented that the aforeſaid 11. <hi>accuſed Members,</hi> were not yet put out of the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> (though moſt unlawful to be done) that ſo the <hi>Schiſmatical Party</hi> in that <hi>Houſe</hi> might carry on their <hi>grand Deſign</hi> of an <hi>accurſed Toleration,</hi> with the fuller and freer <hi>concurrence of Votes</hi> and <hi>Suffrages,</hi> when once it was ripe enough to be diſcuſt and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and in the <hi>Houſe;</hi> And becauſe, alſo, the City of <hi>London</hi> would not conſent to <hi>alter the power of their Militia,</hi> nor lie altogether, idle, ſecure, and ſupine, from making ſome juſt preparations for the defence of their often and highly menaced and threatned City to be plundered, burned and made a prey to this <hi>Army of Saints</hi> (which defence, God knows, at beſt, was very little and inconſiderable) but eſpecially by occaſion of a <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Engagement,</hi> whereinto divers moſt honeſt and religious <hi>peaceable Citizens, Seamen</hi> and <hi>Apprentices</hi> of <hi>London</hi> and the parts about it (only by reaſon of the <hi>Armies</hi> often and inſolent threats and formidable preparations for war, and frequent incroachments and approachings neer unto their City) had entred into, to ſtand to their <hi>Covenant</hi> (which above all, this <hi>Army of ſweet Saints</hi> could not endure) made with God and the three Kingdoms, to endevor with their lives and fortunes, the defence of their true Religion, City and Liberties, to preſerve the Kings perſon and dignity (now in great danger, in both, he being in the <hi>Armies</hi> wicked cuſtody) and to bring his <hi>Majesty</hi> to the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> for the perfecting of a happy and <hi>wel-grounded Peace,</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ogether, and all theſe, upon ſuch terms and conditions as the <hi>Commiſſioners of the Parliaments of both Kingdoms</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhould ſee moſt fit and ſalubrious for the beſt good of all the three Kingdoms; and this <hi>Petition and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement</hi> they purpoſed (according to their honeſt and orderly cuſtom of proceeding in theſe kinds) to preſent to their <hi>Common Councel,</hi> with their humble and peaceable deſires that the <hi>Lord Maior, Aldermen</hi> and <hi>Common Councel,</hi> if they liked and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed thereof would be pleaſed in all their names, and, then, joyntly of the <hi>whole City</hi> to preſent the ſame to the <hi>Par.</hi> for their ratification and eſtabliſhment of their deſires therein. But, the Army, inſtantly, having private intelligence thereof (by ſome falſe brethren, even whiles this buſineſs was but in the <hi>Embrio</hi> of it)
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115676:12"/>with all poſſible ſpeed poſts away their moſt imperious Demands (rather indeed, <hi>Commands</hi>) to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> forthwith to ſuppreſs, this deſperate and dangerous, yea, this bloody and <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable deſign</hi> (as thus they moſt craftly and frightingly termed it) and upon this, to change the City Militia, which was done all in one day; and to cal the <hi>Contrivers</hi> and <hi>Actors</hi> therein, and main <hi>Abettors</hi> thereof, into ſevere queſtion, as <hi>traiterous fomentors</hi> of a <hi>Second or New War</hi> (becauſe, indeed, ſuch a juſt defence as this was like to prove, and would, as they juſtly feared, mightily impede, yea, utterly break the neck of the <hi>Armies grand Deſign</hi>) or elſe they with all their <hi>Martial power,</hi> muſt of neceſſity come up preſently, and compel and inforce it. Beſides, to aggravate their accuſations againſt the City, the Army had gotten perfect intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, that (about or ſomewhat before this time) the Lord Maior, Aldermen and Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> had ſent Letters and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed them with their names, into <hi>Kent</hi> &amp;c. to crave thoſe their neighbors aſſiſtance to help to defend the City, if force were made againſt it by the Army; which, it ſeems became a foul of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in the City, and moſt worthy to be ſeverely puniſht, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Treaſonable Deſign againſt the Army: juſt, as if a man, his houſe being in danger of fire to be burned down, or of theeves and rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers coming to aſſault him in his houſe, ſhould ſend forth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to his neighbors, to ayd and aſſiſt him againſt thoſe dangers and juſt fears of his, and for this cauſe the theeves and robbers ſhould make a ſore complaint of him, how they were wronged thereby, and procure the Maſter of the houſe and his Servants (or aſſociates) to be puniſhed for thus endevoring to ſave and preſerve their houſe and goods from rapine and ruine.</p>
            <q>
               <l>If ever, now, Sea Saints turn'd Sinons vile,</l>
               <l>A Parliament and City to beguile.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Hereupon,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> in the fifteenth place, the <hi>Parliament</hi> (being now apparently forced by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of this <hi>overpowering Army,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the help of the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Secturies</hi> in the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi>) voted all thoſe that were <hi>Author</hi> of and <hi>Actor</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Engagement</hi> (though but intended) to be <hi>Traitors,</hi> and to be proceeded againſt with the loſt of their lives undeſtates; And preſently painted and publiſhed an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> to have them all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> all over the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115676:12"/>City, by Drum and Trumpet; At which moſt ſtrange proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Army</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> the City in general being mightily diſcontented, preſently ſent the <hi>Lord Maior, Aldermen</hi> and <hi>Common Councel</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> to petition the <hi>Parliament</hi> for a preſent removal of divers grievance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and chiefly for an inſtant revocation, or repealing of that (conceived, unjuſt) <hi>Ordinance</hi> aforeſaid. But, eſpecially, very many <hi>Apprentices</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>young men</hi> (with divers others mixed mong them) went alſo the ſame day to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in a tumult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous manner (as the Army called it, though multitudes petitioning make not a tumult, but have been very, much countenanced and encouraged, yea and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of by a Declaration of the Parliaments formerly ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t forth.) But therein, alſo, the honeſt Citizen were moſt wickedly abuſed by many <hi>Cavaliers, Malignants,</hi> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Sectaries too,</hi> who mixed themſelves among the honeſtly young men, the more to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe them and their work, but all of them unarmed, thus urging the <hi>Parliament</hi> for the inſtant <hi>nullifying</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Ordinance,</hi> and ſo much the more vehemently they urged the immediate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance hereof, becauſe they then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> (nay heard for certain) a preſent adjournment of the <hi>Parliament</hi> was reſolved on, and therefore they preſſed the more mightily upon <hi>Both Houſes of Parliament</hi> (whiles they were yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſitting) with earneſt cries and intreaties, to all that paſt in or out, for the nulling of that ſevere and (as they humbly conceived) moſt unjuſt <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> againſt them, only for action (as they conceived and in their conſciences were aſſured, according to their <hi>Covenant;</hi> which their deſires, being, at laſt, though indeed, with much ado, obtained in <hi>Both Houſes,</hi> and the <hi>Apprentices,</hi> thereupon, being, now, contentedly departed all to their own homes; yet, upon this, the <hi>Parliament</hi> being by <hi>Both Houſes</hi> adjourned, the 2 Speakers of <hi>Both Houſes</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and other Members thereof, both <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> &amp; <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</hi> preſently deſerted the <hi>Parl,</hi> and ſlew away, yet the diſorder and tumult was raiſed (after all the Petitions were gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) meerly o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainly, I ſay, by <hi>Sectaries</hi> of the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> and by ſundry eminent <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> as can be proved, (as in mighty pretended fear) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our <hi>Army of Saint,</hi> for Safeguard and Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, But, the reſt of the <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Westminster</hi> returning and ſitting ſtil, on the day de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mined by the whole <hi>Parliament,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115676:13"/>where finding their two <hi>Speakers</hi> to have deſerted the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> they inſtantly choſe them two <hi>other Speakers,</hi> and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly (as they might indeed) according to their duty to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, proceeded in their work and way. Beſides all this, to make the matter yet more unhappily offenſive to them and us, and to make the City ſeem, at leaſt, in pretence, more foul and faulty; It pleaſed the Lord, that it ſo fell out, that the <hi>Lord Maior, Aldermen</hi> and <hi>Common Councel</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> hearing for certain of the <hi>Armies</hi> extraordinary haſtning toward <hi>London,</hi> with all the ſtrength they were able to make ready, eſpecially of their horſe, their foot and artillery haſtning alſo after with all expedition, and raiſing the Countries to follow them and joyn with them; and (therefore) I ſay, ſitting in <hi>Councel</hi> at their <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of defence againſt the anger of the <hi>Army;</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> a fudden quarrel was raiſed there, by a moſt rude rubble of <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>ſeditious Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> under a colour and pretence of <hi>preſenting a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Common Councel</hi> for a <hi>colourable-peace,</hi> of their own making; which rude multitude ſo unſufferably and baſely abuſed valiant and wel-deſerving <hi>Major General Poyntz,</hi> a brave and victorious <hi>Commander</hi> of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> in the <hi>North of England,</hi> who at that time came forth of the <hi>Militia</hi> (then alſo ſitting in the ſaid <hi>Guild-Hall</hi>) thinking to paſs peaceably through the <hi>Hall,</hi> but, I ſay, was ſo intolerably abuſed by the <hi>Sectaries,</hi> who as ſoon as ever they ſaw him come forth, cryed out, <hi>No Poyntz, no Poyntz,</hi> pull'd him violently by his ſcarlet Cloak, asking him, if he had payd for it, yea ſome of them (as 'tis moſt credibly reported, by eye-witneſſes) kicking him on his breech, yea and ſmiting him on his head, in high ſcorn and contempt, in ſomuch that the <hi>heroick-spirited Gentleman,</hi> as a <hi>Soldier,</hi> alſo, could no longer indure them, but that drawing his ſword, other ſwords were alſo drawn, one was ſlain, and divers others woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and much hurt was done among them, (But, before this, a party of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax's</hi> Army of peaceable Saints had fain upon certain of Sir <hi>Robert Pyes</hi> Soldiers, who were diſpoſed of by our Parliament for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and lay quietly quartred at <hi>Detford,</hi> and ſlew divers of them, wounded others of them, and made the reſt of them to fly for their lives; and ſo were the firſt themſelves
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115676:13"/>that ſhed blood in a hoſtile manner which I hope juſtice wil in time require an account of from ſome of them.) But I ſay all thoſe foreſaid accidents on our ſide, moſt unhappily falling out together, as ye have heard, made up the mouths of the <hi>Armies</hi> gaping hopes for the more full compleating of their main Deſign, <hi>viz. The City.</hi> For, the <hi>Army</hi> makes all this (now) an unqueſtionable cauſe of their ſpeedy marching up to <hi>London</hi> to ſtil their tumults, as they gave out; As if the <hi>City of London</hi> (famous for their admirable and unparaleld <hi>Government</hi> over the whole world, for theſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred years) had not been able to paciſle any tumultuous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, ſuddenly riſen up among them &amp; by their own power, and juſtice of the City to apprehend &amp; bring to tryal the <hi>Authors</hi> of any ſuch Commotions, either in the <hi>City,</hi> or at the <hi>Parliament,</hi> without the injurious help of an ambitious and aſpiring <hi>Army,</hi> by whoſe examples (yea and provocations too) of rebellion, in a ſpecial manner, againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> at firſt, theſe ſad diſaſters have thus fain out among us; As that excellent <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Religions Retreat,</hi> pag. 13. wel obſerveth, in theſe his own very words: <hi>We may all well obſerve, That all the late ſtirs, which the Army cals Mutinies and Treacheries, tending to New Wars</hi> (whereof they ſo loudly cry out againſt us contioually) <hi>and ſpilling of blood, have aroſe, in oppoſition to them; for if they would have layd down their arms, as they ought to have done at the Parliaments ſeveral Commands, no question, but every true ſubject would willingly have layd down his head upon his pillow, and gladly have taken his reſt,</hi> eſpecially after ſuch late deſtructive bloody broyls, is he had ſo ſmarted by: But here now I wil conclude this Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, with this <hi>diſtick,</hi> in taking notice of the moſt remarkable <hi>bypocriſie</hi> of this our <hi>Army of Saints</hi> forſooth, who are ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to fall upon <hi>others</hi> as <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>ſeditious Traitors</hi> for only endevoring juſtly to defend themſelves from the violence of their <hi>Army,</hi> they forgetting themſelves to be the firſt and worſt <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> and <hi>Rebels</hi> againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and ſo conſequently the whole Kingdom.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Thus, now, theſe Saints, like Hypocrites proceed,</l>
               <l>Others to laſh, for what Themſelves ſhould bleed.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now in the foreſaid interim,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> the <hi>City of London</hi> ſeeming alſo to put themſelves upon a preparation (at leaſt, I ſay, as twas hoped,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115676:14"/>but falſly) though not to fight, yet to defend themſelves and City from threatned plundering and invaſion of the <hi>Army,</hi> if it, ſhould attempt the ſame againſt it; In all they now did, they were but like <hi>Janus,</hi> with two faces under one hood, look two ways at one time; Or like a <hi>Waterman,</hi> who at the ſame inſtant row one way, and look another: For, they ſeem earneſtly to procure power of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and had enough given them (had they acted accordingly) by an excellent <hi>Ordinance of Parliament,</hi> to have bravely ſtrengthned their City within, and to have curbed and kept under any falſe-hearted Brethren, either of the <hi>Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> or <hi>Schiſmatical Parties,</hi> from hurting them within, or help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Army</hi> without. Upon which <hi>Ordinance,</hi> they choſe noble &amp; ever to be honored <hi>Major Gen. Maſſey</hi> to be their <hi>General</hi> of all the City forces within, and the <hi>Parliament</hi> had appointed and order'd, by their <hi>Committee</hi> for the <hi>ſafety of the Kingdom,</hi> noble General <hi>Poyutz</hi> for his aſſiſtance to command the Horſe and <hi>Reformadoes</hi> without; thus they ſeemed ſeriouſly and in good earneſt to liſt Horſe and Foot in S. <hi>Jameſes</hi> and <hi>Tuttle-fields;</hi> made a huge pudder in the City by ſhutting up their ſhops, beating their drums up and down in the ſtreets, and making a mighty <hi>pretence</hi> of a powerful oppoſition of the <hi>Army;</hi> but, all to no purpoſe; for, in all this mean ſeaſon, underhand Petitions for peace were framed, and followed hard; <hi>Sectaries</hi> fled out of the City to their <hi>Army of Saints:</hi> crying out to the <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Commanders,</hi> that all the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>godly party</hi> in <hi>London</hi> were now quite undone, if the <hi>Army</hi> ſpeeded not, with all poſſible haſt to <hi>London</hi> for their preſervation; yea, and the City it ſelf perſiſted in their <hi>Treaty</hi> with the <hi>Army</hi> by their <hi>Commiſſioners,</hi> among whom, were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially two <hi>long-breath'd Orators,</hi> (<hi>voces, praeterea nihil;</hi> as the <hi>Country-man</hi> ſaid of his <hi>Nightingals</hi>) who as 'tis generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, like ſubtile <hi>Ambide xters,</hi> caſt in ſo much <hi>coloquintida</hi> of their frothy <hi>Oratory,</hi> as ſpoil'd all the pottage of the Cities ſolid preſervation, (not, but that we bleſs God moſt heartily for <hi>Peace,</hi> 10000 times rather than <hi>War,</hi> and like wel the <hi>work done,</hi> though not the <hi>manner of the work-mens doing of it</hi>) for, they, undoubtedly applied a playſter far worſe then the difeaſe, made a peace or pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with the <hi>Army,</hi> upon no conditions at all, on their own part, no, not ſo much as for ſaving the City from plundering
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115676:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>(ſave only by word of mouth from Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> his bare promiſe, and that in ambiguous and Delphick expreſſions) yet, by Gods providence, indeed, their <hi>gold chains</hi> and <hi>full cheſts</hi> were, for the preſent, preſerved) But, upon many, yea any, and all conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons advantageous to the <hi>Armies party;</hi> even ſuch, as none (ſure) but <hi>mad men</hi> or <hi>fools</hi> in the Army would have refuſed; And, thus, moſt ignommiouſly, leaving renowned <hi>General Maſſey,</hi> and noble <hi>General Poyntz,</hi> with all their abuſed <hi>Reformadoes,</hi> in great ſtraits, who were all forced to fly, preſently, for their own ſafety; and hereby alſo having brought the honeſt <hi>Preſbyterian Party,</hi> both in the <hi>Parliament</hi> and in the <hi>City,</hi> into great inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and no little danger; yea, and, that which hath in a moſt <hi>high meaſure ſtained</hi> the reputation of the <hi>City,</hi> and (beſides and above all the reſt) brought them under a moſt <hi>black cloud of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumy</hi> and <hi>diſgrace,</hi> that they moſt unworthily condeſcended to the <hi>Army</hi> to null, diſavow, and diſclaim, their <hi>City Declaration,</hi> a rare peice, had it been religiouſly and courageouſly ſtood unto, even a ſecond <hi>Covenant;</hi> O, <hi>in this,</hi> my Soul grieves for the <hi>ſhame,</hi> of this, late, ſo <hi>honorable a City,</hi> thus now made ſo <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honorable:</hi> All which, the face of a <hi>Conſiderable Army</hi> or Horſe and Foot (which, the City might eaſily have raiſed, had it acted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfully, and in good earneſt) appearing in a body, with their brave and honeſt <hi>Commanders</hi> (as, ſuch they were, indeed, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the lying <hi>Sectaries</hi> ſlanders moſt injuriouſly caſt upon them) had moſt unqueſtionably, by <hi>the Lords mercy</hi> diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and avoyded; yea notwithſtanding <hi>Southwarks</hi> treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous trick, and the <hi>Tower-Hamblets</hi> baſe defection and <hi>neutrali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> Whereas, now, by this means, the <hi>freeſt</hi> and <hi>moſt famous</hi> City in the world is totally (though, yet, inſenſibly) made a <hi>cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated prey</hi> unto an incroaching and <hi>ſelf-ſeeking Army</hi> of diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling <hi>Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Self-Do, Self-Have; our common Proverb goes:</l>
               <l>Ah, ſtupid <hi>London,</hi> Cauſe of Thine own woes!</l>
            </q>
            <p>Thus, now, then,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> the <hi>General</hi> and his <hi>Army</hi> of <hi>ſweet Saints</hi> having (by notorious ſubtilty) as it were vanquiſhed and enſlaved ſo rich, ſo rare, ſo populous and famous a City, and that, without ſtriking one ſtroak for it; and thereby, alſo, having made it as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous, as ever it had formerly been renowned and glorious: He
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115676:15"/>now brings back again with him, <hi>Both the Speakers</hi> of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> who were, lately, fled from the two <hi>Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (as was formerly toucht) together with the reſt of the <hi>Members of Both Houſes,</hi> both <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> (who had deſerted the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as aforeſaid, and in that abſence of theirs with the <hi>Army,</hi> had ſate, like the <hi>Oxonian Junto,</hi> at <hi>Sion-Houſe,</hi> between <hi>Hounſlow</hi> and <hi>Branford,</hi> and there entred into a ſolemn Engagement with the Army againſt the two Houſes of Parliament, ſitting in their abſence, which they ſubſcribed, and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now extant in the Parliament; and contrived a <hi>Declaration</hi> againſt the fixed <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> which ſate ſtill, there, as it was their duty, in full peace and freedom, all the time of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers abſence, which was from about <hi>July</hi> 26. to <hi>August</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. and went forward in their juſt and legal <hi>Parliamentary</hi> proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings) But the <hi>General,</hi> I ſay, and his <hi>Army of innocent Saints</hi> (unwilling to do violence to any man, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.14.) with a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible and ſtrong hand or power of Horſe and Foot, brought back thoſe <hi>other Members</hi> who had deſerted the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, ſet them in their ſeats and places in <hi>Parliament;</hi> who being ſo ſet, immediately proteſt againſt the proceedings of the <hi>Members of Both Houſes,</hi> that ſate, in their abſence, and would have declared all that the <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Westminſter</hi> had done, in the time of their abſence, to be null and illegal. But (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that, now, the <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> was every day ſtrongly ſurrounded by a ſtrong guard of the <hi>Armies</hi> Horſe and Foot, as was conceived, to o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>aw them: Yet, the <hi>Parliament</hi> putting the <hi>Question</hi> to the <hi>Vote,</hi> it was clearly carryed in the <hi>Negative,</hi> at leaſt four or five times, and that, ſometimes, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 40 voyces, That they ought not to be null, but were juſt and legal; till at laſt, the Army having certain knowledg thereof, and much vext thereat, preſently ſome in the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> (as 'tis credibly reported) threatned the fixed Members, <hi>That if their Votes could not, the long-ſword ſhould carry it for them:</hi> And, immediatly after, the <hi>Army</hi> (to ſecond and confirm thoſe words) ſet out a <hi>Declaration,</hi> upon the <hi>Thurſday,</hi> in Sir <hi>Thomas Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax's</hi> own name, proteſting therein, that, if thoſe moſt honeſt <hi>Preſbyterian</hi> fixed <hi>Members</hi> continued to ſit in the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and there to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to <hi>Vote,</hi> as they did, the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> would come,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115676:15"/>with all its power, and force them out, and dap them up in faſt hold (let all the world judg now what a free <hi>Parliament</hi> this is) as the <hi>Armies Captives,</hi> or <hi>Priſoners of War,</hi> upon which furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous threats on the very next day, being <hi>Fryday,</hi> divers of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious fixed <hi>Members,</hi> moſt unworthily (as we conceive) for very fear left the <hi>Houſe;</hi> yet, all things conſidered, it was wel for them that they went away; for, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it was then credibly ſaid and aſſured, on that next Fryday morning <hi>Cromwel</hi> came to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and the Officers of the Army into the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, to ſee their Declaration made good, and though excepted againſt in the diſpute, they would not withdraw, being backt with 1000 Horſe in <hi>Hyde-Park,</hi> one Troop at the door, and <hi>Deſborough</hi> who commanded the Horſe being ready at the door to receive Command to ſeize upon the Members, if they were not able to carry it by Vote: But upon their abſence, the <hi>fled-Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> (the greateſt number whereof, 'tis wel known were <hi>Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> and ſuch like neuters and ſiders with them) took advantage thereof, and that ſame following <hi>Fryday</hi> morning put the <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> again to the <hi>Vote,</hi> and now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> laſt carryed it, this only <hi>one time,</hi> in the <hi>Affirmative;</hi> againſt the others <hi>four or five times</hi> in the <hi>Negative;</hi> and this ſingle Vote of theirs muſt ſtand and null and illegal all that had been done in <hi>Parliament,</hi> in the time of their abſence, to the unſpeakable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ment of the <hi>Parliament, City</hi> and <hi>whole Kingdom,</hi> whereon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by and by; but now to look back to the <hi>Army</hi> of our <hi>humble-hearted Saints:</hi> The <hi>Army</hi> having (as was forementioned) all rubs now, removed, and their way fair before them to do what they pleas'd, and having quickly ſear'd away the <hi>City-guard</hi> from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and confined them, now, within their own <hi>City-walls,</hi> and intreated the City <hi>Trained-Bands</hi> (whether they would or not) to give them poſſeſſion of all the <hi>City For<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and <hi>Lines of Communication,</hi> whereof now they were become <hi>Maſters;</hi> Shortly after, the <hi>whole Army</hi> en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the City, and that in a moſt Martial and <hi>triumphant equipage;</hi> The <hi>General</hi> himſelf, like a <hi>ſecond Caſar,</hi> or ſome famous <hi>Roman Conſul</hi> riding through the City in princely pomp and ſtately triumph, amended by <hi>his whole Army,</hi> who rode all of them with <hi>green Bays</hi> and <hi>Laurels</hi> in their hats, in token of Conqueſt, both before and behind him, and immediatly before
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115676:16"/>him rode 8 or 10 of his <hi>brave conquering Officers,</hi> in arms, all <hi>bare-headed,</hi> even like as to a <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Keiſar,</hi> indeed; the <hi>Lord Maior</hi> alſo, <hi>Aldermen</hi> and <hi>Common Councel</hi> of the City, having, before, met his <hi>Excellency</hi> at <hi>Hyde-Park,</hi> to kiſs their <hi>golden-fetters,</hi> and to tender to his <hi>Excellency</hi> the promiſed gift of a <hi>golden Baſon and Ewer of a</hi> 1000 l. <hi>price,</hi> together with the invitation of him and his brave Commanders, to a ſumptuous feaſt within their City (yea and as tis credibly affirmed thoſe two fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Ambi-dexters would have the City to have had invited the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators by name, unto this feaſt, a moſt baſe abſurdity) in requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of their kindneſs in thus eaſily reducing their City into <hi>ſordid Captivity;</hi> yea, and the <hi>Common people,</hi> through the whole City, filling the ſtreets, as the <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> thus, paſt along, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring, and applanding, with the higheſt <hi>punegyricks</hi> that their greedily gazing eyes could manifeſt (like ſo many ſottiſh and dull <hi>Iſſachars Aſſes</hi>) to their, late, moſt mean <hi>Martial Servants,</hi> now become their <hi>Martial Maſters.</hi> Which, ſitly brings this proper <hi>diſtick</hi> into my thoughts.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Stark Dolts and Fools, I do them (justly) hold,</l>
               <l>That love their Fetters, though they be of Gold.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> now, in the eighteenth place, for a ſpeedy and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous Demonſtration of the truth of theſe premiſes, and to ſhew thee the ſad beginnings of this poor Cities <hi>growing,</hi> if not future <hi>groaning</hi> miſeries and calamities; The <hi>Parliament</hi> having made the <hi>General</hi> (in part of preſent requital of his late good ſervice to them) <hi>High-Conſtable</hi> of the <hi>Tower of London;</hi> with power alſo to put in, as his Subſtitute, whom he pleaſed, to be <hi>Lieutenant</hi> thereof; the <hi>General,</hi> to ſhew his zeal and fervour for the yet more effectual promoting of the <hi>grand Deſign,</hi> fore-ſpoken of; going, now, to the <hi>Tower</hi> to take poſſeſſion thereof, and having been with all honor and humanity entertained, by the noble, and (both for his <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Martial Proweſs</hi> in the face of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my) moſt highly deſerving then preſent <hi>Lieutenant</hi> of the <hi>Tower,</hi> Colonel <hi>Weſt,</hi> at a ſumptuous feaſt, or dinner of purpoſe, there, provided for him; and after many ſeeming friendly ſalutations, and hoped cordial regreets, mutually paſt between them at the table; After dinner, this new <hi>High-Conſtable</hi> having the keys of the <hi>Toner</hi> delivered to him; and notwithſtanding alſo that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115676:16"/>the <hi>Lord Major, Aldermen,</hi> and <hi>Common Councel</hi> had highly recommended to his <hi>Excellency,</hi> the ſaid noble <hi>Lieutenant Col. Weſt;</hi> yet he preſently diſplaces this brave and every way wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerving <hi>Colonel,</hi> and gave the keys and <hi>Lieutenantſhip</hi> of the <hi>Tower</hi> to a pretty young Pageant-ſtripling, <hi>viz.</hi> one M. <hi>Titchburs,</hi> a hopeful young man, indeed; and one that (to be ſure) is very likely to be herein very uſeful to the <hi>Tower</hi> precinct and incloſure, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſave the hyre of a Preacher there, in that himſelf has a dexterious faculty in preaching already. After this, alſo, the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> cauſes the <hi>City Militia</hi> to be <hi>new-moulded</hi> and <hi>modelld</hi> into a former condition, to wit, of having the <hi>Schiſmatical Militia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> reinveſted into the power of the <hi>Militia,</hi> in ſatisfaction and pacification of the late <hi>quarrel</hi> and complaint, herein, againſt the honeſt <hi>Preſbyterian Citizens</hi> who had by a <hi>full</hi> and a <hi>free Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> obtained the juſt expulſion of all ſuch <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> from bearing any Office of power or truſt in our <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as either refuſed to take the <hi>Covenant,</hi> or were Enemies to the <hi>Ends</hi> and <hi>Intentions</hi> thereof, in point of <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> and <hi>godly Church Government,</hi> according to an <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> formerly voted, printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>authority,</hi> I ſay, of a <hi>full</hi> and <hi>free Parliament;</hi> but, now, thus alter'd and nullified by the over-awing power of this <hi>Army of Saints</hi> upon this their Parliament.</p>
            <q>
               <l>That Proverb's (thus) made good by th'General;</l>
               <l>Might orecomes Right and Weaklings muſt to th' Wall.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And, now,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>City</hi> being pretty wel brought under the terror and power of the <hi>Army,</hi> the <hi>Army</hi> begins ſtiffly to proſecure the conſummating of the <hi>Sectaries great Deſign</hi> of <hi>Toleration</hi> and <hi>Liberty of Conference to All:</hi> And wel knowing they could not throughly effect this til the <hi>Parliament</hi> were throughly purged of all the oppoſite and active <hi>Preſbyterian Members</hi> therein, therefore (as was briefly toucht before) they vehemently ſtil, inveigh againſt about, at leaſt 70 others of the more honeſt and pious party of the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> who alſo ſate and acted in the <hi>Parliament</hi> in the abſence of the others, who, moſt unworthily, deſerted the <hi>Parliament</hi> and fled to the <hi>Army;</hi> which, now, like an <hi>Army of Saints,</hi> indeed, ful I beleeve, of <hi>Serpentine Craft,</hi> but not of <hi>Dove-like Innocency</hi>) proteſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115676:17"/>their <hi>ſitting</hi> in the <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>voting,</hi> there, as <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Houſe,</hi> and moſt earneſtly and urgently threatned again and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain (even by their beggarly <hi>Agitators</hi> alſo of their <hi>Army</hi>) to thruſt and force them out, as it were by head and ſhoulders, even by a day of their appointment, or elſe they could forbear no longer, but would immediatly force them out, if they durſt, ſtil, <hi>abide</hi> and <hi>vote</hi> there: Inſomuch that now, at laſt, not only the firſt 11. <hi>accuſed worthy Members</hi> were forced to ſly away for fear of them, (whereof one moſt eminent Member, much honored Sir <hi>Philip Stapleton,</hi> is (ſince) dead, beyond the Seas, by this <hi>Armies of diſſembling Saints</hi> moſt bold and bloody perſecution of them, and whoſe moſt innocent blood, I hope, the Lord, the moſt righteous Judg, wil, when he makes inquiſition for blood, remember, and require at their <hi>hands;</hi> but alſo the moſt, if not all the reſt of the other 70 moſt worthy <hi>Members</hi> have been (thus) enforced to forſake the <hi>Houſe,</hi> and to deſert that truſt which the Kingdom and Counties for which they were choſen, had impoſed and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted on them. <hi>An affront,</hi> I beleeve, <hi>unparalell'd,</hi> and <hi>far tranſcending</hi> all <hi>preſidents</hi> of all <hi>former ages</hi> and <hi>Parliaments</hi> that ever this Kingdom ſaw, ſince it was a People and Nation; And yet it is a high indignity offered to this <hi>Army of Saints,</hi> to ſay or think, that ſuch a chaſt and modeſt Army as this is hath forced, if not raviſhed the Parliament of its Virgine Power and Priviledges, or that they have any <hi>ſinful</hi> or <hi>ſiniſter deſigns</hi> or <hi>evil intentions</hi> in all or any of theſe their moſt remarkable <hi>Rebeſſions</hi> againſt the <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church</hi> of God: and who (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all theſe their moſt inſolent and arrogant actings, as aforeſaid) would have us to be <hi>charily</hi> tender of <hi>judging</hi> of them, and <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably</hi> to be both <hi>perſwaded,</hi> yea and <hi>aſſured</hi> that they intend no evil, but all good unto us. Whereas, on the other ſide, the <hi>least</hi> and moſt <hi>lawful actings</hi> of any of the <hi>Preſbyterian Parties,</hi> either in <hi>Parliament</hi> or <hi>City,</hi> even for moſt juſt <hi>ſelf-defence</hi> and <hi>preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> are cryed out upon with open mouthes and reiterated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives to be moſt <hi>bloody, hides us,</hi> and <hi>heynous treaſons, rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and <hi>fomentings</hi> of a <hi>ſecond, new, and moſt bloody War</hi> againſt the <hi>Army</hi> and therefore againſt the whole <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, brings, now, here, moſt fitly, into mind, that moſt perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently appliable <hi>Apologue,</hi> to this our preſent purpoſe of the <hi>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115676:17"/>ſhrifting</hi> of the <hi>Lyon, Wolfe,</hi> and the <hi>Aſſe,</hi> which was thus. The <hi>Lyon, Wolfe,</hi> and the <hi>Aſſe,</hi> would needs go to ſhrifting or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing of their faults one to another; yea, and be Judges of one anothers faults, and deſert of puniſhments thereon. The <hi>Lyon</hi> began, and acknowledged, that indeed he had preyed upon many wild beaſts in Woods and Forreſts, as his naturall food, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which he could not live, but had never medled with any men, to devour or hurt them; So ſentence was given by the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Judges herein; that ſurely this indeed was the <hi>Lyons</hi> natural food, and being naturall unto him thus to do, it was ſit it ſhould be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned in him. Then the <hi>Wolfe</hi> came to ſhrift, before the <hi>Lyon</hi> and the <hi>Aſſe;</hi> and he confeſt indeed, that he had oftentimes devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red both men and beaſts that came in his way, and ſpared none whom he could maſter and overcome: but yet truly, that this was his naturall food, by which he alſo lived, and without which he could not ſubſiſt; whereupon, ſentence muſt be given by the <hi>Lyon</hi> and the <hi>Aſſe,</hi> that truly this was a heynous evil in the Wolf; but yet in regard it was the <hi>Wolfes</hi> nature to devour and tear in pieces, all that came within his reach, he ought therefore to be likewiſe pardoned therein. Then the <hi>Aſſe</hi> coming to ſhrift himſelf before the <hi>Lyon</hi> and the <hi>Wolfe</hi> his Judges, acknowledged and freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that he had never hurt any, either men or beaſts; only he remembred, that once his Mr. that owned him, riding upon him on Pilgrimage, and having ſtraw in his ſhoos, and ſome of the ends of the ſtraw hanging looſe out of his ſhoos, and he being very hungry in the way, reached his mouth to ſome of the ſtraws, and eate them as he went on: Whereupon, both this <hi>Lyon</hi> &amp; the <hi>Wolfe</hi> inſtantly cryed out, that this was a moſt ſoul and unpardonable offence, and aggravated this fact to be exceeding heynous thus; What? ſay they, Eate the ſtraw out of your Mrs. ſhoos, that ſhould have kept his feet warm, and that whiles he was riding on Pilgrimage to perform his holy Devotions! O this was a moſt intolerable fact, and worthy of ſevereſt puniſhment: and therefore for it he muſt ſuffer death, and ſo was devoured by them both. The Application I leave to the judicious and religious Reader: only take this Diſtick, and I have done with this Obſervation.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Cobwebs take ſmall, Great flies break looſe, and gon,</l>
               <l>And ſome may ſafely on ſteal then ſome look on.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:115676:18"/>And now in the twentieth and laſt place,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> to cloſe up all, with an invincible Argument and Demonſtration of a <hi>Deſperate Deſign,</hi> moſt Subtilly and Clandeſtinely carryed on by this moſt <hi>deceitful Army of Saints,</hi> againſt the moſt honeſt and innocent <hi>Preſbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Party</hi> (which hold cloſs to their ſacred and ſolemn <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi>) and ſo by a moſt clear and undeniable Conſequence, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the work of a pure and powerful <hi>Reformation,</hi> both in <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline:</hi> Notwithſtanding, all the loud and lying out-crys of the <hi>Sectaries</hi> of all kinds, formerly againſt <hi>Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any Saints</hi> or <hi>Christians for Conſcience ſake,</hi> even in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>fact:</hi> Yet, how hath this <hi>Army of Saints</hi> themſelves (now that they have begun to get power into their hands at this time) bin and are the <hi>primary,</hi> if not <hi>only Cauſe of the Perſecution,</hi> (even unto death already of divers) not only of the XI Renowned and moſt Faithful <hi>Patriots</hi> of their Country; both for <hi>Counſell</hi> and <hi>Warr:</hi> but alſo of 70. more of them at one blow: and now more lately of divers both <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> impeached <hi>of high Treaſon,</hi> for ſitting in the <hi>Parliament,</hi> for the good of the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> (according to their <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Covenant</hi>) whiles others fled from it: Together with divers other moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionably worthie and Eminent and Excellent Citizens of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> old and young, who both in their <hi>perſons</hi> and <hi>purſes,</hi> in <hi>Wars</hi> abroad, I ſay, and <hi>Counſels</hi> at home have layd out themſelves in a <hi>high meaſure:</hi> and yet now at this time, divers of them are <hi>clapt up in priſon, Impeacht of high Treaſon,</hi> and ſome forſooth, of <hi>high Miſdemeanours,</hi> and thus their lives and eſtates brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to much danger, to the utter ruinating (as much as in the malice of their <hi>Sectarian Adverſaries lies</hi>) of themſelves, their wives, and deareſt babes, and little Children, and divers others, yet more Eminent, Pious <hi>Preſbyterian Citizens</hi> (fatter morſells for the mouths of <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>miſchief</hi> to feed on) are ſtil threatned to be called in queſtion for their lives and eſtates: Which threatning is now alſo more lately put into execution in no ſmall meaſure, by the Impeachment and Impriſonment of the <hi>Lord Major of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Ald. Adams, Ald. Bunce, Ald. Langham,</hi> and other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent and Excellent Spirited Citizens, upon pretence of high Treaſon (for, as for that petty Impeachment of high Miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, there muſt not be ſo low a deſcention: For that will not
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115676:18"/>raiſe ſumms of money big enough to pay the Armys Arrears) that thus thoſe worthy <hi>Patriets</hi> of that (late) moſt knowned City, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the whole world (though now under a Sable cloud of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace) may like ſo many ſpunges, be ſquiez'd with deep and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſines and large ſumms, for being ſo <hi>Loyal</hi> and <hi>Faithful,</hi> as to adventure to defend themſelves and their City (according to Conſcience and Covenant) againſt the Martial orders, and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Premonitions of an <hi>Army of Saints</hi> who muſt have it ſo, and their pact <hi>Parliament</hi> (therefore) muſt act it ſo; and let God and the world judg, if this be not the very <hi>quinteſſence</hi> of black <hi>ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,</hi> and of breach of former (ſeeming) ſerious and often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, <hi>to live and dye</hi> with the City of <hi>London</hi> at that time, when they had extream need of their perſons and purſes, of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth which, the moſt noble City of London was then moſt prodigall, even to admiration. Yet now, ſee how moſt ingratefully (to ſay no worſe) they are repayd and rewarded, and all to pleaſe a Seditious and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Army,</hi> Yea, and many mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of our moſt famous and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Preſbyterian Ministers</hi> of the City of <hi>London,</hi> are (as we hear for certain) threatned, to be call'd in queſtion alſo, (yea and ſome are already queſtioned, as <hi>Doctor Burgeſs, Mr. Sedgwick,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Byfeild,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Ienkins</hi> Miniſter of Chriſts-Church) and to be puniſht in their <hi>perſons</hi> (an they are, and long have bin moſt vilely and abominably in their <hi>purſes</hi> and <hi>livelihood,</hi> under pretence (by our wicked <hi>Sectaries</hi>) of unlawfulneſs of paying <hi>Tythes</hi> to the eternall ſhame, and indelible infamie of thoſe that ſhould, but will not help it) and all and every of them, thus ſuffering, only for acting according to their ſacred and ſolemn <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> and the moſt exact and upright rule of a good <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> backt by the authority of <hi>Parliament</hi> alſo (if at leaſt (now a days) we know what and where a <hi>Parliament</hi> is, or ought to be) and that alſo juſtified, to be moſt legal and authentick by 5. ſeverall <hi>votings of a free Parliament,</hi> againſt <hi>one ſingle vote,</hi> of a moſt apparent <hi>Army-forced,</hi> and <hi>over-awed Parliament,</hi> which hath thus made all thoſe actings of the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>City Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable,</hi> by their Remonſtrance upon the Thurſday, and their force of 1000. Horſe at <hi>Hade-Park,</hi> on the next day being Fryday; and this alſo made both our <hi>Covenant</hi> and our <hi>Parliament,</hi> a meer ſnare to honeſt-hearted and Religious people (as I think,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:115676:19"/>hath bin abundantly fore-ſpecified) by the intolerable and unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> and <hi>double-dealing</hi> of the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> of theſe our days, both in <hi>Parliament, Army, City</hi> and <hi>Country;</hi> Who (thus) think to mock God, as they hope to gull and abuſe too credulous men. If this be not <hi>perſecution</hi> (and that in a high nature) for <hi>honesty</hi> and <hi>Conſcience ſake,</hi> I know not what is. And if theſe be <hi>principles</hi> and <hi>practiſes of Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Sectarian Saints,</hi> and of the <hi>Anabaptiſtical-Godly-Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> (as they like proud <hi>Phariſaical-Juſticiaries</hi> call themſelves) I pray God deliver me and all my Friends from ſuch <hi>White-De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils,</hi> in <hi>Saints-ſhapes,</hi> from ſuch <hi>bloody Wolves</hi> in <hi>ſheeps-skins.</hi> To conclude al, hath not this precious <hi>Army of Saints,</hi> now of late alſo, moſt craftily and cunningly contrived more and more to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found all, by their deep-digged, &amp; even palpable <hi>Ieſuiticall Machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations,</hi> as low as hel it ſelf, in their laſt moſt ſtrangely woven <hi>deſign</hi> (even to the deep aſtoniſhment of the wiſeſt of men among us, and to the very poſing of the quinteſſence of wit it ſelf) in ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conveighing our moſt unhappy Soveraing King from <hi>Hampton-Courts</hi> endurance, to the impregnable priſon of the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> thus hurrying this poor Prince from poſt to pillar, even as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb is, <hi>Out of the Frying-pan into the fire;</hi> as we all have great cauſe to fear (as knowing the ſpirits of the <hi>Sectaries</hi> in generall, ſo wel as we do) by thus either traiterouſly enforcing, or craftily perſwading his Majeſty, for the avoiding of the devouring <hi>Gulf Charibdis,</hi> to daſh againſt the <hi>Sharp Rock,</hi> of death-threatning <hi>Scylla,</hi> according to that old verſe, and (if ever) now too truly verified Adagy.</p>
            <q>Incidit in Scyllam, cupi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns vitare Charibdim.</q>
            <p>Thus in Engliſh.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Hee's daſht' gain <hi>Scyllas</hi> Rock and quite deſtroyd,</l>
               <l>Hoping <hi>Charibdis</hi> Whierl-pool to avoid.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And certainly this is too evidently (at leaſt in our preſent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted apprehenſion and juſt fear) poor <hi>King Charles</hi> his ſad condition, toſt and tumbled up and down, by moſt Trayterous and Rebellions <hi>Sectaries and Schiſmaticks,</hi> and now under a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of avoiding the deadly danger (which in truth, I am apt enough to believe, was too really intended) of the Lilb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> faction, the ſo moſt audatious Agitators (I had almoſt ſaid Agitraitors) of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115676:19"/>the Army, that rude rabble of Levellers indeed, as they are fitly termed by his Majeſty himſelf in his Declaration, ſaid to be his, left on the table at <hi>Hampton-Court:</hi> Under this colour and pretext, I ſay, to hurry his Majeſty into the graſping paws and Captivity of <hi>Cromwel</hi> and his <hi>Confederates, Hammond</hi> the preſent <hi>Governor of the Iſle of Wight,</hi> being his <hi>hopefully</hi> intended <hi>Son in Law,</hi> thus to make up their own mouths, and work out their own weal [if poſſibly it may be] though with the inevitable ruin and deſtruction of a, thus, poor, tottering, torn, and moſt miſerably di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> if the Lord in his inſinite meer mercy and grace, interpoſe not to our miraculous preſervation: We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus now by theſe <hi>wofull factions</hi> and <hi>fractions</hi> both among our ſelves, and in this diſſembling <hi>Saint-like Army,</hi> brought into the ſame, or into a worſe condition then King <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> was by another <hi>Army,</hi> and with him <hi>enforced</hi> to cry out and ſay: <hi>Lord we know not what to ſay or do, neither is there any ſtrength in us, but our eyes are only up unto thee.</hi> And thus far we all ſee they have moſt undenyably already proceeded: How much farther, yet, they will wade into this their <hi>unfathomed Ocean of deceit, couſnage</hi> and <hi>abuſe</hi> of Gods people, the Lord only knows: To which moſt righteous Judg of the world, who <hi>ſits</hi> in heaven, and <hi>ſees,</hi> and <hi>ſmiles,</hi> and <hi>laughs</hi> them to ſcorn, and hath them in <hi>moſt high deriſion,</hi> and who in his own due time, will by his power, [through their own <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>Hipocriſie</hi>] break them in pieces like <hi>Potters-veſſells,</hi> with his <hi>Iron-mace,</hi> of irreſiſtible juſtice, I leave them. And ſince this is moſt certain, <hi>Pro.</hi> 21.30. <hi>That there is no wiſdom, nor understanding, nor Counſel, that can prevail againſt the Lord;</hi> Therefore I wil ſay only thus much in brief, to all my dear <hi>Preſbyterian Brethren,</hi> in the words of <hi>Moſes; Stand stid</hi> [with godly <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> holy <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Faith,</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>Reſolutions,</hi>] <hi>and ſee the Salvation of our God,</hi> which he undoubtedly will in his own due time, and by his own beſt way, work for thee. Amen and Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115676:20"/>
            <head>A Merricall Corollarie, upon the Armies full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the Scripture-Properties of true Saints and Chriſtian Souldiers, prefixed in the Front of this Treatiſe.</head>
            <l>THus [Reader] thou haſt had a ſight</l>
            <l>By this moſt brief ſurvay,</l>
            <l>Of th' <hi>Armies Actions</hi> juſt and right</l>
            <l>
               <hi>The clean contrary way.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>How they have done to <hi>Other Men</hi>
            </l>
            <l>(as Chriſt to them did ſay)</l>
            <l>As <hi>Other Men</hi> ſhould do to <hi>Them</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>The clean contrary way.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>How they have kept the Rule, moſt wiſe,</l>
            <l>Which <hi>Paul</hi> before them lays,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>To do no Ill that Good may riſe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>All clean contrary ways.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And how each <hi>Small Appearing Sin</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>Army</hi> doth gain-ſay;</l>
            <l>Abhorr and Shun, juſt praiſe to win</l>
            <l>
               <hi>The clean contrary way.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Yea, how <hi>intact</hi> from <hi>doing wrong</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>Army</hi> is, I ſay,</l>
            <l>And how <hi>exact</hi> from a <hi>Slanderous-Tongue</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>The clean contrary way.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Yea, here thou ſeeſt what friends they are</l>
            <l>To th' Crown and <hi>Regal-Sway,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To <hi>Monarchy</hi> what love they bear</l>
            <l>
               <hi>The clean contrary way.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>What fervent love to Government</l>
            <l>They piouſly diſplay,</l>
            <l>With Godly-Order, how content,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>The clean contrary way.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Then to this <hi>Army</hi> of pure <hi>Saints,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Who, faſt and loſe thus play;</l>
            <l>Let us give thanks, free from Complaints,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>The clean contrary way.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="encouragement">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115676:20"/>
            <head>A Scripture Cordiall and Encouragement to all Conſtant <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertan Covenanters,</hi> againſt all temporizing <hi>Diſſemblers</hi> and <hi>Backſliders.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>RIghteous art thou, O Lord, when I plead with thee; Yet let me talk with thee of thy judgments: Wherefore doth the way of the wicked proſper? Wherefore are all they happy that deal very treacherouſly with thee and thy children? But thou, O Lord, knoweſt all thine, thou ſeeſt that and trieſt their hearts, how they are toward thee: And will pull thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Enemies out like beaſts for the ſlaughter; and thou prepareſt them for a day of certain Deſtruction. <hi>Jerem. 12.1, 3.</hi> Art not thou from everlasting, O Lor my God, mine Holy-one? We ſhal not die, O Lord, thou hast ordained the wicked for judgment: And O mighty God, thou haſt eſtabliſht them for correction. Thou art of purer eyes then to behold evill, and canſt not look upon iniquity. Wherefore then O Lord, lookeſt thou upon them that deal treacherouſly, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thy tongue, when the wicked devoureth the man that is more righteous then he? <hi>Habakkuk 1.12, 13. Thus with holy</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid (Pſal. <hi>73.</hi>) <hi>Gods Children oftentimes become</hi> envious, <hi>when they ſee the</hi> proſperity of fools and woked men, <hi>untill they retire into the</hi> Sanctuary <hi>of God and conſult with his</hi> unerring Word, <hi>then they clearly ſee and underſtand</hi> the end of theſe men, <hi>to wit, how</hi> God ſees them in ſlippery places, caſts them downe into ſud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain Deſtruction, ſoon cuts them downe like the graſs that withereth; ſo that in a moment, he is not, and the place where he lately flouriſhed, like a green Bay-tree in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, that cannot be found. <hi>Pſal. 37. Thus</hi> the hope of <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites</hi> ſhall certainly periſh, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be cut off and caſt away, as a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders-web. <hi>Job 8. So that in due <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me, Gods Children ſhall in holy exultation, have juſt cauſe to rejoyce in the</hi> juſtice <hi>and</hi> righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs <hi>of our God, and to ſay</hi> Pſal. <hi>58.</hi> Verily there is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for the righteous, verily there is a God that uprightly judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the earth.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Magna, imo maxima eſt veritas (quoniam veritatis dominus</l>
               <l>Eſt potentiſſimus et prudentiſſim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>) &amp; ſuper omma praevalebit.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
